<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Act of the Convention of Estates: holden at Edinburgh the fifteenth of August 1643. for the loane and taxt</title>
            <title>Laws, etc. 1643-08-15</title>
            <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92509</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1139A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203709</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899202</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899202</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152724</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92509)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152724)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2318:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Act of the Convention of Estates: holden at Edinburgh the fifteenth of August 1643. for the loane and taxt</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc. 1643-08-15</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12, 11-12, 9-10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Evan Tyler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Taxation --  Law and legislation --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="legislation">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152724:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ACT OF THE CONVENTION OF ESTATES:</hi> Holden at Edinburgh the fifteenth of Auguſt <hi>1643.</hi> for the Loane and Taxt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orſameikle as the Kings Majeſtie and Eſtates of this Realm, in the late Parliament, taking to their conſideration the Rebellion in Ireland, and danger upon that occaſion threatned againſt the Proteſtant Religion, Did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and out of their affection to the Kingdome of England, make offer to the ſaid Kingdome of a ſupply of ten thouſand men from this Kingdom, for ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of that Rebellion, To be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by the Parliament of England, according to the Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made thereanent by the Commiſſioners ſent from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Kingdome, With inſtructions ſent from the Lords of Privie Councell thereof; And accordingly the ſaid ſupply being put over upon the great charges of this Kingdome, ſuch have beene the great neceſſities &amp; wants of that Army, as well Officers as Souldiers, not only through default of their ordinary pay, but alſo of victuall in the ſpareſt meaſure, and all other neceſſaries, That the Lords of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie Councell, unto whom the care of that army was entruſted by the Parliament, and who did accordingly undertake for the ſame, Have been put to great trouble and charges, both by engaging themſelves, and with them alſo the Commiſſioners for the peace and common burdens, As alſo by their joynt invitation of the well-affected ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this kingdome to contribute ſums of money for entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152724:2"/>of that Army, and payment of the arreares thereof, which they are obliged to pay with the ordinary annuall rent; And howſoever conſiderable ſums have beene by their painfull endevours received, Notwithſtanding, ſuch have been the preſſing miſeries of that Army, in regard of the unhappy diſtractions in England, diſabling the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therof, according to their obligement to entertain them, as they have expreſt in their ſeverall Declarations ſent to the Lords of His Majeſties Privie Councel; And ſuch have been the difficulties occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the ſaids Lords of Privie Councell, Commiſſioners of peace, and common burdens, touching the farther entertainment of that Army, which they found unpoſſible for them any longer to undergo, as they were moved from their affection to His Majeſties ſervice, and ſenſe of the diſtreſſe of their brethren, For this and other the like extreme exigencie, neerely importing the good of this Kingdome, to call this Convention of Eſtates, by whoſe authority they might more warrantably proceed in matters of ſo great importance: And the ſaids Eſtates having accordingly taken to their conſideration the condition of the ſaid Army, and the whole courſe and procedure concerning the ſame, as is before expreſt:</p>
            <p>Therefore, and for divers other conſiderations moving the ſaids Eſtates, they have thought fit, ſtature and ordained, Like as by thir preſents they ſtatute and ordaine, The ſum of twelve hundred thouſand marks Scots money, together with the ſum of one hundred thouſand marks mony foreſaid, as allowance for charges of ingather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame, to Collectors, Clerks, and others neceſſary members, and for allowance of exemptions for mortifications, and the Lord Chancellour and fifteene ordinary Lords of the Seſſion, perſons exeemed, as is after ſpecified, To be uplifted by way of Loane, out of the ſeveral Sherifdomes and burrowes of this Kingdome, in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as is after divided: <hi>viz.</hi> The ſaids Burrowes one ſixth part of the principall ſum, extending to 200000. marks, and the ſeverall Sherif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of this Kingdome to pay the remanent of the ſaids ſums, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to a particular roll made and ſet downe thereanent, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in preſence of the ſaids Eſtates by the Lord Chancellour, to remain in Record in the bookes of Convention and Collection; Which whole ſums of money to be lent, as ſaid is, as well to Burgh as landward, ſhall be delivered to the Collectors, and others having power from the ſaids Eſtates, betwixt the date hereof, and the ſecond day of February next to come 1644. yeares.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the ſums of money preſently to be lent, are not to be ingathered aff the ſhires, as taxations have been, or by the diviſions of Temporalities and Spiritualities, But rather is thought fit that the ſame may be uplifted out of the lands, teinds, and others, as they lie locally in every Sherifdome promiſcuouſly, conforme to the ſaid roll ſubſcribed as ſaid is.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is thought neceſſary that ſeverall Sub-collectors be appointed through the whole Kingdome, in ilk ſhire or ſhires one or more; Which Sub-collector or Collectors, ſo to be appointed,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152724:2"/>ſhall be charged with the whole ſums of moneyes to be lent by the ſhire or ſhires where he or they ſhall be Collector.</p>
            <p>And to the effect the ſaids Sub-collectors may have letters of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe againſt the ſeverall perſons to be contained and ſet downe in the Rolls after mentioned:</p>
            <p>Therefore the ſaids Eſtates have nominate the perſons following: <hi>viz.</hi> For the Sherifdome of Orkney, <hi>Thomas Buchanan</hi> of Sound, Sheriffe of Orkney, and <hi>Patrick Smith</hi> of Braco, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter the reſt of the ſhire to chooſe their own Conveeners) <hi>James Baikie</hi> of Tankernes, <hi>Adam Ballinden</hi> of Stane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, <hi>James Mudie</hi> of Melſetter, <hi>Patrick Balfour</hi> of Fearey, <hi>Edward Sinclar</hi> of Gyre.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdomes of Innernes and Cromertie, ſir <hi>John Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenzie</hi> of Tarbet, maſter <hi>Alexander Mackenzie</hi> of Kilcowie, Convee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter the reſt of the ſhire to chooſe their own Conveeners) <hi>Walter Innes</hi> of Innerbraiky, <hi>Coline Mackenzie</hi> of Kincraig, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Monro</hi> of Obſtail, <hi>Alexander Dumbar</hi> of Bennetſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, <hi>Robert Innes</hi> of Roskeene, <hi>Hugh Fraſer</hi> of Belladrum, <hi>John Grant</hi> of Lurgie, <hi>John Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cleud</hi> of Dunevegan, <hi>Neil Macneil</hi> of Baro, ſir <hi>James Fraſer</hi> of Bray, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Roſſe</hi> of Pitcanie, <hi>Walter Roſſe</hi> of Kindroſſe, <hi>Thomas Roſſe</hi> of Prieſthill.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Caitnes, ſir <hi>James Sinclar</hi> of Murtil, <hi>David Sinclar</hi> of Dun, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter the reſt of the Shire to make choice of their owne Conveeners) <hi>James Sutherland</hi> of Forſe, <hi>David Cogle</hi> of that Ilk, <hi>John Sinclar</hi> of Scrab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>James Sinclar</hi> of Brymnes, <hi>John Innes</hi> of Stuiſter.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Sutherland, ſir <hi>Alexander Sutherland</hi> of Duffus, <hi>Robert Murray</hi> of Pulroſſie, Conveeners for the firſt meeting and thereafter the reſt of the ſhire to make choice of their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veeners <hi>Robert Gray</hi> of Creich, <hi>Walter Murray</hi> of Pitgourdie, <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gordoun</hi> of Carrell, <hi>Hugh Mackye</hi> of Skowrie, <hi>Robert Gray</hi> of Boltoun.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Nairn, <hi>George Campbel</hi> brother to the Laird of Caddel, <hi>William Dollace</hi> of Contra, Conveeners for the firſt meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (and thereafter the reſt of the ſhire to make choice of their owne Conveeners) <hi>Hugh Roſſe</hi> of Kilraok, <hi>Alexander Broddie</hi> of Lethin, <hi>John Grant</hi> of Moynes, <hi>William Roſſe</hi> of Clava, <hi>Thomas Dumbar</hi> Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Grange, <hi>Patrik Paplay</hi> of Broomhill.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Elgin, ſir <hi>Robert Gordoun</hi> of that Ilk, ſir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Innes</hi> of that Ilk, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter the reſt of the ſhire to make choice of their owne Conveeners) ſir <hi>Alexander Sutherland</hi> of Duffus, maſter <hi>John Hay</hi> Provoſt of Elgin, <hi>Alexander Dumbar</hi> of Weſtfield, <hi>Ninian Dumbar</hi> of Grangehill, <hi>James Grant</hi> of Frewchie, <hi>John Cuming</hi> of Racowcas.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Aberdeen, the Lards of Drum and Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorth to be Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter thoſe of the Shire to chooſe their owne Conveeners) <hi>Robert Farquhare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of Innercald, <hi>John Irwing</hi> of Beltie, <hi>Alexander Straquhane</hi> of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152724:3"/>Glenkendie, ſir <hi>William Forbes</hi> of Craigievar, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Davidſon</hi> of Cairnie, ſir <hi>Gilbert Meinzies</hi> of Pitfodells, <hi>Thomas Erskin</hi> of Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toddrie, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Robert Farquhare</hi> of Munie, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Robert Gordoun</hi> of Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurg <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gordoun</hi> of Cokclarochie, <hi>John Owdnie</hi> of that like, <hi>James Hay</hi> of Muryfauld, <hi>Robert Irwing</hi> of Fedret, <hi>William Keith</hi> of Clakriach.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Bamffe, <hi>Alexander Ogilvie</hi> of Kempcarne, <hi>Thomas Abercrombie</hi> of Skeith, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and therafter thoſe of the Shire to chooſe their own Conveeners) <hi>James Stewart</hi> of Ordeins, <hi>Walter Grant</hi> of Mellers, <hi>Alexander Ogilvie</hi> of Knok, <hi>James Barcley</hi> of Kinminnettie, <hi>Alexander Leſly</hi> of Auchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doun, <hi>John Grant</hi> younger of Ballindalloch.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Kincardin, ſir <hi>Alexander Falconer</hi> younger fiar of Hackerton, ſir <hi>Alexander Cairnegie</hi> of Pittaro, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter thoſe of the Shires to make choice of their own Conveeners, ſir <hi>Robert Grahame</hi> of Morphie, ſir <hi>Gilbert Ramſay;</hi> of Balmain, <hi>Robert Keith</hi> of Whiterigs, Sheriffe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of Kincardin, <hi>Patrik Falconer</hi> of Newton, <hi>John Barcley</hi> of John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, <hi>John Falconer</hi> fiar of Newton.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifedome of Forfar, <hi>Robert Arbuthnet</hi> of Findowry, ſir <hi>Alexander Carnegie</hi> of Ballnamoon, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter the reſt of the Shire to make choiſe of their owne Conveeners) <hi>John Lord Loure, Peter Young</hi> of Seaton, <hi>William Ruthven</hi> of Gairn, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>James Durhame</hi> of Pitcairo, <hi>James Vicount</hi> of Dudop, <hi>William Durhame</hi> elder of Grange, M<hi rend="sub">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Durham</hi> of Omaquhie <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Maxwell</hi> of Telin, <hi>James</hi> Lord Couper <hi>James Crichton</hi> of Ruthven, ſir <hi>VVilliam Blair</hi> of Bagillo <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lyon</hi> of Brigton, <hi>Henry Mauld</hi> of Melgume,<hi>Thomas Fothrengham</hi> of Dununne.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Perth, The Lairds of Inſhbraikie, and Inſhture, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to mak choiſe amongſt themſelves.) <hi>Thomas Blair</hi> of Baltheyok, ſix <hi>Thomas Ruthven</hi> of Frieland, <hi>John Oliphant</hi> of Bachilton, <hi>Peter Hay</hi> of Leyis, ſir <hi>Patrick Ogilvie</hi> of Inſhmartin, ſir <hi>Robert Campbell</hi> of Glenorquhie, <hi>Alexander Menzies</hi> of Comrie, <hi>Patrick Ratra</hi> of Cuaighall, <hi>Gilbert Campbell</hi> of Keithik, <hi>John Blar</hi> of Ardblair, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Patrick Murray</hi> fiar of Ochtertyre, <hi>James Drumond</hi> of Milnab, ſir <hi>John Hadden</hi> of Glene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, <hi>William Sterling</hi> elder of Auchyle.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Fyfe, and Kinros, the Lairds of Scots<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craig, and Danemiln to be Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter to make choiſe among themſelves) ſir <hi>James Halket</hi> fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar of Pitfirrane, <hi>William Monteeth</hi> of Randeford, <hi>John Henderſon</hi> of Fordell, <hi>Robert Dempſter</hi> of Balbougie, ſir <hi>George Hamiltoun</hi> of Blaik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn, ſir <hi>John VVeymis</hi> of Boegy, M<hi rend="sub">r</hi> 
               <hi>Robert Ayton</hi> of Inſhedairnie, ſir <hi>Andrew Skeen</hi> of Halyeardis, ſir <hi>James Arnot</hi> of Fairnie, ſir <hi>Iohn Aiton</hi> of that ilk, <hi>Iames Macgill</hi> of Rankelour elder, <hi>George Hay</hi> fiar of Nachtoun, ſir <hi>Thomas Myreton</hi> of Cambo, M<hi rend="sub">r</hi> 
               <hi>Iames Ried</hi> of Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lethie, <hi>VVilliam Forbes</hi> younger of Rires, ſir <hi>VVilliam Douglas</hi> of Kirknes, and <hi>David Balfour</hi> of Ballo.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152724:3"/>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Sterling, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Murray</hi> of Polmaes, <hi>John Rollok</hi> of Bannokburn, Conveeners for the firſt meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and thereafter the reſt of the ſhire to make choice of their owne Conveeners, ſir <hi>Thomas Nicolſon</hi> of Carnok, <hi>William Livingſtone</hi> of Waſtquarter, <hi>William Roſſe</hi> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>John Sterling</hi> of Harbert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, ſir <hi>James Livingſton</hi> of Bancloth, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Stirling</hi> of Glorat, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Kinked</hi> of Archinreach, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun</hi> of Baldoure, <hi>William Blair</hi> of Fenik, <hi>John Lennox</hi> of Cairneſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Cunningham</hi> of Balindalloch, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Robert Naper</hi> of Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crewch, <hi>James Stirling</hi> of Balwill, <hi>Alexander Cunningham</hi> of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quhane.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Clakmannan, ſir <hi>Charles Erskin</hi> of Bandeth, ſir <hi>Robert Bruce</hi> of Clakmannan, and ſir <hi>Alexander Shaw</hi> of Sauchie, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to make choice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, Maſter <hi>Robert Bruce</hi> of Kennet, <hi>James Hadden</hi> of Myreton, <hi>William Graham</hi> of Hilton, <hi>William Reid</hi> of Craig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heid.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Edinburgh, ſir <hi>Archibald Johnſton</hi> of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſton, and the Laird of Libberton, to be Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to chooſe among themſelves, ſir <hi>Patrick Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miltoun</hi> of little Preſton, ſir <hi>William Scot</hi> of Clerkington, <hi>David Macullo</hi> of Guidtries, M<hi rend="sub">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Inglis</hi> of Nether-Cramond, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>David An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſoun</hi> of Hill, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Cant</hi> of Pentland, <hi>Marke Kerſſe</hi> of Cokpen, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Samuell Johnſton</hi> of Scheans.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Linlithgow, The Lairds of Daundas and Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bachlaw, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to make choice among themſelves, <hi>William Drummond</hi> of Riccarton, ſir <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Murray</hi> of Livingſtoun, <hi>George Dundas</hi> of Dudingſtoun, ſir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Drummond</hi> of Medop, Maſter <hi>George Dundas</hi> of Maner, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>James Hamiltoun</hi> of Weſt-port, <hi>Samuell Drummond</hi> of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowrie.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Hadingtoun, ſir <hi>Patrick Hepburne</hi> of Wach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun, and ſir <hi>Adam Hepburn</hi> of Humbie, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to chooſe among themſelves, M<hi rend="sub">r</hi> 
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Hepburne</hi> of Smeitoun, <hi>Patrick Inglis</hi> of Elvingſton, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>James Sydſerffe</hi> of Ruchlaw, <hi>John Hepburn</hi> of Craig, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Alexander Hay</hi> of Bara, <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Cairnes</hi> of Pilmoore, <hi>George VVood</hi> of Neumilnes.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Berwik, The Lairds of Aitoun and Blaika<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Conveeners, for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to chooſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, <hi>George Auchirlek</hi> of Cumledge, <hi>Alexander Home</hi> of Reſtoun, <hi>Alexander Home</hi> of Rollandſtone, <hi>James Home</hi> of Caſtell-law, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Alexander Home</hi> of Saint Leonards, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>George Home</hi> of Kymergem, <hi>William Home</hi> of Linthill.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Roxburgh, The Lairds of Stobbs and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to make choice amongſt themſelves, ſir <hi>Walter Riddell</hi> of that ilk, Maſter <hi>George Douglas</hi> of Bonne-Jedbrugh, <hi>John Ker</hi> of Lochtour, <hi>Robert Pringle</hi> of Stichel, <hi>Iohn Scot</hi> of Gorranberrie, <hi>VValter Scot</hi> of Gaudie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152724:4"/>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gilbert Ellot</hi> of Craigend, <hi>James Pringle</hi> of Buckholme, <hi>Iohn Scot</hi> of Heidſhaw, <hi>Iohn Rutherfoord</hi> of Capehope, <hi>Robert Land-lands</hi> of that ilk, <hi>Walter Riddell</hi> portioner of Bewly, <hi>Andrew Bell</hi> of Mow, <hi>Andrew Key</hi> of Sinles.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Selkirk, The Lairds of Harden and Whitſleid Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to chooſe amongſt themſelves, <hi>James Pringle</hi> of Torwoodlie <hi>Iames Pringle</hi> of Whitebank, <hi>Neill Scot</hi> of Gallaſcheills <hi>William Scot</hi> of New-wark, <hi>Robert Scot</hi> of Hartwoodmyres, <hi>Robert Scot</hi> of Bowhill, <hi>Francis Scot</hi> of Synton.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Peibles, ſir <hi>Alexander Murray</hi> of Blakbarronie, ſir <hi>David Murray</hi> of Stonehope, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to make choice among themſelves, ſir <hi>Michael Naeſmith</hi> of Poſſo, Mr <hi>Iames Lawſon</hi> of Cairnmure, <hi>Robert Hunter</hi> of Polmood, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Hay</hi> of Hayſton, <hi>William Govan</hi> of Cardrona.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Lanerk, The Lairds of Belſtane, and Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerff, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, &amp; thereafter to chooſe amongſt themſelves, ſir <hi>Iames Hamiltoun,</hi> of Fingletoun, <hi>Edward Hamiltoun</hi> of Sillertonhill, <hi>Gavin Hamiltoun</hi> of Raploch, <hi>William Baillie</hi> of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin, <hi>Robert Hamiltoun</hi> of Aikinheid. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Crafurd</hi> of Kibbers, <hi>Andrew Hamiltoun</hi> portioner of Overtoun, ſir <hi>William Baillie</hi> of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minton, ſir <hi>William Carmichell</hi> fiar of that ilk, <hi>George Weir</hi> of Blaik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, <hi>Iohn Bannatine</hi> of Corhous <hi>Iames Hamiltoun</hi> of Halcraig, <hi>Iames Winraham</hi> of Wolſtoun, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn Carmichell</hi> Commiſſer of Lanerk, <hi>Iames Hamiltoun</hi> of Sandieholme, <hi>Iames Hamiltoun</hi> of Boigs.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Air, The Lairds of Rowallan, and the Laird of Corsby, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to chooſe amongſt themſelves, <hi>Hew Campbell</hi> of Ceſnoke, <hi>James Chalmer</hi> of Gad-girth, ſir <hi>William Cochrane</hi> of Coudoun, <hi>Allan Cathcart</hi> younger of Cairnehill, <hi>Robert Ferquhar</hi> of Gilmicroft, <hi>Neill Montgomrie</hi> of Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw, <hi>Robert Montgomrie</hi> of Hiſſillheid, <hi>John Crafurd</hi> of Crafurdland, <hi>David Kennedie</hi> elder of Kirkmichell, <hi>Thomas Boyd</hi> of Pankill, <hi>Gabriell Proterfield</hi> of Hapland, <hi>Iohn Cunningham</hi> of Bordland, <hi>Henry Kelſo</hi> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iohn Mac-Alexander</hi> of Corſclayes, <hi>Iohn Macclevin</hi> of Grim-met, Mr <hi>Adam Cunningham</hi> of Priviks.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Wigtoun and ſtewartry of Kirkudbright, The Laird of Garthland, and the young Sheriffe of Galloway, Convee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to make choice among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſir <hi>Patrick Makgie</hi> of Large, <hi>John Makgie</hi> of Balmagie, <hi>William Grierſon</hi> of Bargaltoun, <hi>Alexander Gordoun,</hi> of Erleſtoun, <hi>Iames Roſſe</hi> of Banneill, <hi>Iohn Makculloth</hi> of Mertoun, <hi>Iohn Fullerton</hi> of Carletoun, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Makcullo</hi> of Drummorell, <hi>George Glendonning</hi> of Mochrumi <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Gordoun</hi> of Crachlaw <hi>Uchtry Mackdowgall</hi> of French, <hi>Patrick Agnew</hi> of Sewchram, <hi>Richard Mure</hi> of Caſſincarry, <hi>Thomas Makclellan</hi> of Colin, <hi>Patrick Agnew</hi> of Barneweil, <hi>Iohn Stewart</hi> of Shambelly, <hi>William Glendonning</hi> Proveſt of Kirkudbright, <hi>Iames Lafreis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Dumfreis, The Laird of Lag and <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to make choice among themſelves, Mr <hi>George Douglas</hi> of Pymu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152724:4"/>
               <hi>Thomas Ferguſon</hi> of Caitloch, <hi>John Creichtoun</hi> of Crafoord John, <hi>James Douglas</hi> of Mortoun,<hi>William Maxwell</hi> of Steilſtoun, <hi>John Grier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of Chappell, <hi>Hugh Charters</hi> of Glencorſe, <hi>Alexander Ferguſon</hi> of Ile, <hi>James Douglas</hi> of Mouſewall, <hi>Robert Charters</hi> of Dowchra, <hi>James Johnſtoun</hi> of Corheid, <hi>Andrew Johnſtoun</hi> of Locherby, <hi>Matthew Wilſon</hi> of Greenhill, <hi>Francis Scot</hi> of Carteitoun, <hi>John Kennedie</hi> of Halklaithes, <hi>Archbald Dowglas</hi> of Dronock.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Renfrew, the Laird of Grenok, and <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Conveeners for the firſt meeeting (and thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to meet and chooſe amongſt themſelves) fir <hi>Ludowick Hoſtoun</hi> of that ilk, <hi>John Birsbane</hi> of Biſhoptoun, <hi>Alexander Porterfield</hi> of that ilk, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pook</hi> elder of that ilk, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Caldwall</hi> of that ilk, <hi>John Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> of Southbarre, <hi>James Orr</hi> of Langfillie.</p>
            <p>For the Sheriffdome of Dumbartan, the Laird of Fulwood, Convee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for the firſt meeting (and thereafter to chooſe amongſt themſelves) <hi>Walter Makaula</hi> of Ardincaple, <hi>John Naper</hi> of Kilmahew, <hi>Robert Hall</hi> of Fulbarre, <hi>Robert Cochran</hi> of Bellarmik, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Carſhore</hi> of that ilk, <hi>John Colquhoune</hi> of Kilmadymne, <hi>Hugh Craford</hi> of Claverhill, <hi>John Denneſtoun</hi> of Dalquharrie.</p>
            <p>For the Sheriffdome of Argyle, the Lairds of Glenurquhie, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinbrek, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter to chooſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves) <hi>James Campbell</hi> of Arkinelies, <hi>Archbald Campbell</hi> of Kilmure, ſir <hi>Lachlane Makclene</hi> of Dowart, <hi>Archbald Campbell</hi> of Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffnik, Sheriffe depute of Argyle, <hi>George Campbell. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Hector Makneil</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Bute, the Laird of Skelmorlie, Conveener for the firſt meeting, ſir <hi>James Stuart</hi> of Kirktowne, <hi>Ninian Stuart</hi> of Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catton, <hi>Ninian Stuart</hi> elder of Aſhcock, <hi>Hector Bannatyne</hi> of Kaynes, <hi>John Stuart</hi> of Aliſmore, <hi>Neil Makneil</hi> of Kilmore, <hi>John Campbell</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Proveſt of Rothſay.</p>
            <p>Who ſhall conveene with the whole Heritours, Life-renters, Takſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Titulars, proper Wadſetters, Penſioners, Conjunctfiers, Lady tercers, and others, within ilk one of their ſaids Sherifdomes, <hi>reſpectivè,</hi> Or at leaſt with ſo many of the ſaids perſons as ſhall be conveened for the time, upon the firſt Tueſday of October next, as the firſt day of their meeting appointed for the whole ſhires of the Kingdome: And to the effect the ſame may be knowne to the whole lieges;</p>
            <p>It is ordained that the Conveener or Conveeners of the ſhires before named, ſhall cauſe intimate the ſaid meeting at the Market croſſe of the head Burgh of the ſhire with all convenient diligence, and at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Pariſh Kirk thereof, immediately after Divine Service, upon any Sunday preceding the 22. day of September next, and to meet ilk ſhire at the places following: <hi>viz.</hi> The Sheriffdome of Orkney at the town of Kirkwall, the Sheriffdome of Caitnes at the town of Thurſay, the Sheriffdome of Sutherland at the towne of Dornoch, the Sheriffdomes of Innernes and Cromertie at the Burgh of Innernes, the Sheriffdome of Narn at the Burgh of Narn, the Sheriffdome of Elgin at the Burgh of Elgin, the Sheriffdome of Bamf at the Burgh at the Burgh of Bamf, the Sheriff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome lam den day
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152724:5"/>dome of Aberdene at the Burgh of Aberdene, the Sheriffdome of Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cairdine at the towne of Stanehyve, the Sheriffdome of Forfar at the Burgh of Forfar, the Sheriffdome of Perth at the Burgh of Perth, the Sheriffdomes of Fife and Kinros at the Burgh of Cowper, the Sheriff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Clakmannan at the town of Clakmannan, the Sheriffdome of Sterling at the Burgh of Sterling, the Sheriffdome of Renfrew at the the Burgh of Renfrew, the Sheriffdome of Dumbartan at the Burgh of Dumbartan, the Sheriffdome of Argyle at the Burgh of Innerara, the Sheriffdome of Bute at the Burgh of Rotheſay, the Sheriffdome of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerk at the Burgh of Lanerk, the Sheriffdome of Air at the Burgh of Air, the Sherifdome of Wigtoun and Stewartrie of Kircudbright at the Burgh of Wigtoun, the Sheriffdome of Dumfreis at the Burgh of Dumfreis, the Sheriffdome of Roxburgh at the Burgh of Jedburgh, the Sheriffdome of Selkirk at the Burgh of Selkirk, the Sheriffdome of Peibles at the Burgh of Peibles, the Sheriffdome of Berwick at the Towne of Duns, the Sheriffdome of Haddington at the Burgh of Had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington, the Sheriffedome of Edinburgh at the Burgh of Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, the Sheriffdome of Linlithgow at the Burgh of Linlithgow. And there the ſaids Conveeners, or any of them, with ſuch other Commiſſioners as ſhall be conveened for the time, ſhall cauſe call by name and ſurname, the Heritours, Live-renters, Titulars, Takſmen of teinds, proper Wadſetters, Penſioners, Ladie tercers, and others within the ſaid Sheriffdomes, who bruike any benefit to landward, whereby any profit or commoditie ariſeth, And by conſent of them, or moſt part of them conveened for the time, ſhall make choice of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect number of perſons, to be joyned with the foreſaids Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, choſen by the Convention, to the number of eight perſons, in the foreſaids ſhires where there are ſixteen choſen by the Convention, and to the number of three perſons in the reſt of the ſhires, being judicious, conſciencious and underſtanding men, who ſhall (as well theſe nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate as thoſe to be elected) give their ſolemne oathes judicially at their firſt meeting, in preſence of the ſaid Conveener or Conveeners, who are hereby authorized to take their oathes, to doe uprightly and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, according to their beſt knowledge and information in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars folowing.</p>
            <p>With power to the ſaids Commiſſioners, or moſt part of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veened for the time, to make choice of a Clerk for writing and form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the rolls after ſpecified, and doing every other thing incumbent to the charge after following.</p>
            <p>Which Commiſſioners ſo nominate and elected, ſhall uſe all lawfull meanes, according to the time, and if need be, ſhall direct out ſummons at their owne inſtances againſt any perſon or perſons within the ſaid ſhire, to compeere before them, and give them information upon oath or otherwayes, with certification of a pecuniall ſumme, not exceeding fourtie pounds <hi>toties quoties,</hi> in caſe of contempt and refuſall.</p>
            <p>And with power to the ſaids Commiſſioners, to uſe all other legall way to informe themſelves of the juſt and true worth of every perſon or perſons their preſent years rent of this cropt and yeare 1643. to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152724:5"/>landward, as well of lands and teinds, as of any other thing whereby yearly profit and commoditie ariſeth.</p>
            <p>And that the worth of every perſon of perſons, their lands, teinds, and other commodities, where greſſums and entereſſe have been payd, be valued and ſet downe, not onely as they pay to the Heritors, Life-renters, and others their maſters, but as the ſame are worth, and may pay preſently, without reſpect of greſſums or entereſs, and to divide the ſaids rolls in particular Pariſhes, by making a roll for every ſeverall Pariſh within the ſaid ſhire; Which roll ſhall containe every particular perſons name, ſurname, and deſignation, with their ſaids years rent, and commoditie within the ſaid Pariſh, whether in victuall, money, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commodities.</p>
            <p>And the ſaid victuall and commodities to be converted into money by the ſaids Commiſſioners, upon their former oathes, according as in every Pariſh the prices of ſeverall ſpaces of victual and commodities ſhall rule for the time, deducing aff the ſaids rents and commodities, what is paid forth thereof to Miniſters, School-maſters, Superiours, Takſmen, Life-renters, Colledges, and Hoſpitals, which deductions aff the ſaids Life-renters, Takſmen, and Superiours, ſhall be charged upon the ſaids Life-renters, Takſmen, and Superiours, by Articles apart, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with any other rent, if any they have within the ſaid Pariſh.</p>
            <p>As alſo becauſe it is neceſſary to be known what the ſaid deductions of Miniſters and School-maſters ſtipends, and exemptions extends to, It is appointed and ordained, that at the end of every one of the ſaids rolls, Articles ſhall be ſet downe thereof: <hi>viz.</hi> one for the ſaids dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Miniſters and School-maſters ſtipends, and another for the ſaids exemptions of every Pariſh.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe appointed, that in the ſetting downe of the ſaids rolls, this years conſtant land rent ſhall be diſtinguiſhed from the other caſuall rent, whereby yearely profit and commodity ariſeth.</p>
            <p>And for performing and perfecting of the ſaids rolls, the ſaids Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners and others foreſaids, ſhal appoint their ſeverall diets of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, betwixt the firſt Tueſday of October next to come, and the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of November thereafter, which is appointed to be the laſt day peremptorily for perfecting and delivering of the ſaids rols.</p>
            <p>And which rolls ſo perfected and concluded, ſhall be ſubſcribed by the ſaids perſons nominate and to be elected as ſaid is, or moſt part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of conveened for the time, and which particular rols of every particular perſon of every Pariſh, ſhall be kept <hi>in retentis</hi> within the ſaid ſhire in ſome truſty perſon or perſons hands, not to be made publick, nor ſhown except to the Collector of the ſaid Pariſh, who muſt make uſe thereof, in uplifting of the ſums due to be paid by the ſaid Pariſh, unleſſe upon occaſion of queſtion betwixt party &amp; party, or betwixt the ſaid Collector and party.</p>
            <p>And after perfecting of the which rolls the ſaids Commiſſioners ſhal draw up aff the ſaids particular rolls of Pariſhes a generall roll contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as many ſeverall Articles, as there are ſeverall Pariſhes, or parcels of Pariſhes (if any be divided within ſeverall Shires) which Articles ſhall be ſet downe in manner following: <hi>viz. A. B.</hi> for himſelfe and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152724:6"/>remanent Heritours, life-renters, and others within the Pariſh of <hi>D.</hi> for their proper rent of the ſaid Pariſh, extending to the ſum of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> (victuall and others commodities being converted into money) their part of the ſaid Loane extends to <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and ſo forth throughout the reſt of the whole Pariſhes.</p>
            <p>In the which roll there muſt be ſet downe <hi>in camalo</hi> the deductions of Miniſters and School-maſters ſtipends (if any be) in an Article. <hi>Item</hi> in another Article mortified and exeemed rents, if any be.</p>
            <p>And ſiclike in ſetting down of the ſaid Article for the whole Pariſh, it muſt be diſtinguiſhed what thereof is conſtant land rent, and what is caſuall rent.</p>
            <p>Which generall rolls, containing onely an Article for every Pariſh within ilk Shire, being ſo ſet downe and ſubſcribed by the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or moſt part thereof conveened for the time, and containing the ſaids Articles of deductions, and exemptions, and diſtinctions, in maner foreſaid, ſhall be delivered by the ſaids Commiſſioners, or their Clerk, to the Sub-collectors of the ſaid Shire appointed, or to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that effect, betwixt and the ſaid 15. day of November next to come, and by the ſaid Sub-collector, to the Clerk of the ſaid colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that the ſame may be a ground and warrand for raiſing of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thereupon againſt the ſaids Collectors of ſeverall Pariſhes, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons nominate in the ſaids generall rolls for every Pariſh.</p>
            <p>And if any of the ſaids Commiſſioners hereby nominate and to be elected for ſetting down of the ſaid roll, ſhal refuſe to accept, or be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in doing their faithfull diligence therein, It is herefore ſtatute and ordained, that letters ſhall be direct to meſſengers of armes to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and charge every one of the foreſaids perſons to accept the ſaid Commiſſion within 24. hours after they be charged, and to do their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act diligence therein untill the finall cloſe thereof, and to deliver the ſaids rolls ſubſcribed by them betwixt and the ſaid 15. day of Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber next to come, under the paine of rebellion, &amp;c, And if they failȝie, to denounce and eſcheat, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And incaſe the ſaids ſtent rolls ſhall not be ſet down, perfected, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and delivered betwixt and the ſaid 15. day of November next to come. In that caſe letters ſhall be direct againſt the ſaids Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners nominate and to be elected, to pay the whole ſums of money to be lent by the ſaid ſhire, which Commiſſioners are ordained hereby to be the firſt payers thereof, in caſe they ſhall refuſe or failȝie to ſet down, perfect, and deliver the ſaids rolls betwixt and the ſaid 15. day of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember next to come, under the paine of rebellion, &amp;c. and if they failȝie, to denounce and eſcheat, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And it is hereby declared, that in the caſe foreſaid of their neglect, as ſaid is, and of their firſt payment of the ſum to be lent by the ſaid ſhire, In that caſe, and after payment thereof made by them, they ſhall have letters of relief againſt the whole Heritours, Life-renters, and others of the ſaid Sheriffdome, conforme to the roll when it ſhall be made up and ſubſcribed by them, or moſt part o them, as ſaid is.</p>
            <p>It is hereby alſo declared, that it ſhall be lawfull and leiſome to every
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152724:6"/>perſon or perſons, (excepting the Commiſſioners nominate, and to be elected as ſaid is) intereſt in the ſummes to be lent by the ſaid ſhire, who cannot conveniently come to the ſaids meetings, to ſend their Procuratours authorized by them in writ, who ſhall have ſuch like power in doing every thing as they might do themſelves, if they were perſonally preſent.</p>
            <p>It is hereby likewiſe declared, that incaſe any of the Heritours, Life-renters, Titulers, Takſmen of teinds, proper Wad-ſetters or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers within the ſaid ſhire, ſhall not conveene at the day and dayes appointed, or to be appointed for that effect, it ſhall be leiſome to the ſaids perſons hereby nominate, or moſt part of them convened for the time, to make and ſet down the ſaids rolls, perfect, ſubſcribe and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſame, in manner aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And that the ſummes of money ſo to be lent by the ſaids ſhires, may be uplifted and inbrought, It is Statute and Ordained, that letters ſhal be directed for charging the whole ſub-collectours within ilk ſhire or ſhires, to make payment of the whole ſummes of money, due to be paid by the ſaid ſhires, whereof they are or ſhall be appointed Sub-col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours, conforme to the ſaid roll, ſubſcribed by the ſaid Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour in preſence of the ſaid Convention, at the ſaid Terme of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlemas next, under the pain of rebellion, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And for the ſaids Sub-collectours their relief aff the ſhires, It is ſtatute and ordained that letters ſhall be directed, charging the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Collectours of every Parochin within the ſaid ſhire or ſhires, or perſons nominate in the ſaids particular rolls for payment to the ſaid Sub-collectour, or his deputies, of the ſummes contained in the ſaids rolls, and that within twenty dayes next after they be charged, if they be within this Kingdome: And if they be without the ſame, by open Proclamation at the Market Croſſe of Edenburgh, Piere and ſhoare of Leith, upon threeſcore dayes warning under the pain of rebellion, &amp;c. And if they failȝie, to denounce and eſcheit, and to poynd and diſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ȝie, &amp;c</p>
            <p>And for relief of the ſaid Collectour of every ſeverall paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chine or perſons nominate in the ſaids particular rolls, It is hereby ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and ordained, that letters ſhall be directed for payment making to them of the ſums conteined in the ſaid particular rolls againſt every particular perſon or perſons conteined in the ſaids rolls, within eight dayes aſter they be charged, if they be within this Kingdome: And if they be without the ſame, by open Proclamation at the Market Croſſe of Edenburgh, Peire and Shoare of Leith, upon 60. dayes warning under the pain of rebellion, &amp;c. With power to poynd and diſtreinȝie their readieſt goods and geire that ſhall be found upon the ground of any of their ſaids lands, who ſhall not timouſly pay, whether the ſaids goods pertain to theſe liable in the ſaid loane or not, which goods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo poynded, it ſhall not be neceſſary to carry them to the Market Croſſe of the head Burgh of the ſhire, but only to uſe the ordinary way of poynding and appriſing upon the ground of the ſaids lands, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſumme of twenty markes for ilk hundrerh markes failȝie.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152724:7"/>
            <p>And for inbringing of the Burrowes part of the ſaid loane, Ordains letters to be direct, charging the Proveſt and Bailies of ilk Burgh, to make payment of their part thereof (conforme to one roll to be ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the Clerk of the Burrowes, or conform to the old roll.) To the ſaid Collectour generall his Deputes and Officers in his name having his power to receive the ſame at the ſaid Terme above ſpecified, and if they failȝie, to denounce and eſchew it, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And for their relief, that letters be derect, charging the Proveſt, Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and Councel within each burgh to conveen &amp; elect certain perſons to ſtent their neighbours, and the ſaid election being made to charge the perſons elected to accept the charge upon them, in ſetting down the ſaid ſtent upon the ſaids neighbours, and to conveene and ſet the ſame, and to make a ſtent roll thereupon as effeires, within twenty foure homes next after the charge, under the pain of rebellion: And if they failȝie, to denounce and eſcheit, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſicklike, the ſaid ſtent rol being made and ſet down as ſaid is, to charge the Burgeſſes, Indwellers, and Inhabitants within each Burgh, to make payment of their part of the ſaid loan to the ſaid Proveſt and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, Conforme to the ſaid roll to be given out thereupon, within three dayes next after the charge under the pain of rebellion; and if they failȝie to denounce and eſcheit, &amp;c. And if needs be that the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt and Bailies poynd and diſtrenȝie as they ſhall think expedient.</p>
            <p>It is alwayes provided, that no perſon whatſoever be ſtented with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Burgh, for any lands or poſſeſſions which he hath to landwart.</p>
            <p>It is hereby likewiſe declared, that the charges to be given for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſaid loane, may be execute as well againſt theſe that are without the Countrey, as theſe that are within the Countrey before the ſaid terme of payment, but that the execution of denunciation and poynding ſhall not be execute untill the ſaid terme of payment be by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone, and the ſeverall dayes of the charges <hi>reſpectivè</hi> forſaids be alſo bypaſt.</p>
            <p>And in reſpect that the foreſaids whole ſummes of money ſo to be lent, be the ſaids ſhires, and burrowes, Is for relief of the great ſummes of money already taken on as ſaid is, and to be advanced for ſupply of the ſaid army in Ireland, which ſhould be repayed by the Parliament of England out of the firſt end of the arrears due to that army.</p>
            <p>Therefore the ſaids eſtates have not onely ratified and approven the foreſaid act of Councell, with concourſe of the ſaids Commiſſioners, for conſerving the peace and Commiſſioners of the common burthens, but alſo have of new Statute, and Ordained, like as they be thir preſents Statute and ordain that aſwell theſe who have already advanced mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money or victuall, or who have engaged themſelves for payment of the prices of victuall, money, and other proviſion by warrant of the ſaids Lords of Councell alone, Or by warrant of them joyntly with the ſaids Commiſſioners of peace and common burthens, but alſo the whole foreſaids ſummes (whereof the ſaids former advancements are apart) are hereby ordaind to be repayed out of the firſt and readieſt of the ſaids arrears, conform to the tenour, and upon the conditions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152724:7"/>mentioned in the ſaid Act of Councell, with concurſe foreſaid.</p>
            <p>And in caſe the ſame ſhall not be repayed by the Parliament of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land betwixt and the ſaid ſecond day of February next to come, It is hereby ſtatute and ordained, like as the ſaids Eſtates by thir preſents ſtatutes and ordaines, that the whole foreſaids perſons, who have by warrand foreſaid advanced money, victuall, or other proviſion, to the ſaid Army, preceding the date hereof, conforme to the particular count thereof regiſtrate in the books of Convention of the date hereof, ſhall be repayed ilk man of his ſeverall ſums, together with the intereſt thereof, conforme to the tenour of the foreſaid Acts, and that out of the firſt and readieſt of the ſums of money to be uplifted by vertue of this preſent act, and that by the Collector, Sub-collector, and others having warrand and power to receive the ſame, betwixt and the laſt day or February next to come.</p>
            <p>So that it ſhall not be leiſome to the ſaids Collectors or others, to diſpoſe upon any of the ſaids moneyes ſo to be lent, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of thoſe who have lent the ſaid money or victuall, untill they be firſt ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>And incaſe the ſaid Parliament of England ſhall happen not to pay and deliver the ſaids by-gone arreares, at leaſt ſo much thereof as ſhall repay the ſaids ſums ſo to be lent, as ſaid is, betwixt and the firſt day of June next to come, in the year of God 1644. yeares.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing it is agreed and condeſcended unto, that the burthen be equally according to every mans eſtate, In that caſe it is declared, that when the whole valuations of the whole Kingdome ſhall be known in manner and conforme to the rolls above ſpecified:</p>
            <p>Therefore it is appointed and ordained, that a ſurvey ſhall be made of the whole foreſaids rolls, and compared one with another, to the effect it may be ſeene and knowne if any Shire or Shires have paid more out of the hundred marks (victuall and others commodities being turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to money) then other ſhires have, and being ſo found, that ſome may be appointed before this preſent Convention diſſolve, or by the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or by Committees from either of them, to ſee what is the juſt proportion, which according to their foreſaids rents, would fall upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Shire, that theſe who have paid more then their juſt proportion, may have repayment aff the Shires, who have paid leſſe, to be collected and inbrought by ſuch perſons as this preſent Convention, the Eſtates of Parliament, or Committees from either, ſhall appoint.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the foreſaids whole ſummes of mony, aſwell to burgh as land ward, extends to a great ſumme of money, and will be a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable burthen upon this Kingdome, and that the ſame is wholly paid out of the land rents, trade, burrow lands, and other land rent and yearly commoditie, without conſideration or laying any burthen upon money upon bank or annuall rent: Therefore it is ſtatute and ordained, like as the ſaids eſtates, ſtatutes, and ordains that every debtour of money upon annuall rent, aſwell to burgh as landward, ſhal have reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the ſaid terme of Candlemas next, of ſix of each hundreth marks or pounds wherein he is liable of annuall rent to his creditours at the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152724:8"/>ſaid terme, Providing that the remanent of the ſaid annuall rent, out of the which the ſaid debitour ſhall crave retention, ſhall be thankfully paid at the leaſt within three moneths after the ſaid terme of payment of the annuall rent, otherwiſe no retention to be allowed.</p>
            <p>And ſiclike, it is hereby declared, that this preſent act, nor no clauſe therein, ſhall be any ground of ſuſpenſion to any debitour for reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid principall ſums addebted by him, and by-runne annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all rents, but that every creditour may ſute, crave and charge, for the ſame, after the day of payment thereof.</p>
            <p>And it is hereby declared, that if any perſon or perſons within or without burgh, ſhall upon their oath declare to their Magiſtrates with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in burgh, and Commiſſioners of the ſhires without burgh, that they pay annuall rent to ſtrangers dwelling without this Kingdome, of whom they cannot have retention foreſaid, in that caſe, the ſaids Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates within burgh, and Commiſſioners without burgh, ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulk proportionally to the ſaids perſon or perſons, ſuch a part of their loane as they ſhall finde agreeable to equity and reaſon.</p>
            <p>And ſiclike, in reſpect that the foreſaids ſummes of money ſo to be lent, are in hope of payment thereof, from the Parliament of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>It is hereby declared, that the whole creditours within this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, aſwell to burgh and landward, who ſhall grant retention to their debitours, in manner foreſaid. ſhall have their proportionall repayment with the reſt of the Countrie, and that either from his debitours, if it pleaſe the creditour to truſt him therewith, or otherwiſe to take aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from the debitour upon the Parliament of England, as a part of the ſame, due to the debitour for his relief.</p>
            <p>AND becauſe the enemies to Religion and Peace of this Kingdom, are dayly making diviſions, and waiting all occaſions, whereby they may draw to factions, make inſurrections, and ſtirre up others to the diſobedience of the lawes, and common reſolution for the good of Religion, his Majeſties honour and ſafety, and the weale of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Therefore, and for the reaſons contained in the act of the ſaids e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, made anent the leavie of ſome horſe and foot, for preveening of any ſuch diviſions, diſtractions, inſurrections, factions and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the ſaids common teſolutions.</p>
            <p>The ſaids Eſtates have voluntarily granted, ſtatute and ordained, like as they by thir preſents voluntarily grants, ſtatutes, and ordains, A taxt of 120000. l. Scots money, to be uplifted for the entertainment of the ſaids men, horſe and foot to be levied, as ſaid is, in manner, and for the uſe contained in the ſaid Act. Which ſum of 120000. l. money foreſaid, ſhall be paid to the ſaid generall Collector, his Deputes and Officers, and others having power and warrand from him, at the ſaid terme of Candlemas next: <hi>viz.</hi> one ſixth part thereof, extending to the ſum of 20000. l. by the Burrowes of this Kingdome, and the remanent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, extending to 100000. l. by the ſeverall Shires of this Kingdome, conform to a particular roll thereof, ſubſcribed by the ſaid Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152724:8"/>in preſence of the ſaid Convention of Eſtates.</p>
            <p>FOR inbringing and ingathering whereof, the ſame maner of way ſhall be followed, and the ſame kind of letters direct, the like diligence uſed and received, as for the foreſaids ſummes of money hereby lent for the ſupply of the Army in Ireland, conforme to the preceding te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this preſent Act.</p>
            <p>And it is ſtatute and ordained, that no ſuſpenſion ſhall be granted to any perſons whatſoever, without conſignation of the ſums charged for in the Clerk of the ſaid collection his hand, unleſſe the reaſons thereof can be inſtantly verified or made notour at the paſſing of the ſaid Bill, either <hi>in preſentia</hi> in the time of Seſſion, or by foure or five of the Lords of Seſſion in time of vacance, To the which ſuſpenſions the ſaids Lords of Seſsion ſhall be onely Judges, in ſuch forme and manner as they are, and have beene in matters of Taxation.</p>
            <p>It is hereby ſtatute and ordained, that the generall Collector ſhall take ſufficient and reſponſal caution from every Sub-collector to do his exact diligence in every thing committed to his charge, as wel in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of money, as in in all other diligence, conforme to the bands to be made by them and their Cautioners thereanent.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe ſtatute and ordained, that the Collectors of every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſhall either be a ſufficient and reſponſall man himſelfe, or otherwiſe ſhall give ſufficient caution for his intromiſsion and diligence, The which diligence to be done as well by the ſaids Sub-collectors, as by the ſaids Collectors of Pariſhes <hi>reſpectivè,</hi> is hereby underſtood to be all ordinary execution of horning regiſtrate in due time, and poynding, untill they be ſtopped by deforcement, are to be received for diligence alannerly.</p>
            <p>Like as it is hereby ſtatute and ordained, that the ſaid Collector ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſhall receive the ſaids diligence of regiſtrate hornings in due time, and executions of deforcement from the ſaids Sub-collectors and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors <hi>reſpectivè,</hi> providing the ſame be delivered to the ſaid collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour generall, before the fifteenth day of March next to come, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes no diligence to be received, but they to be liable for payment <hi>in ſolidum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is likewiſe ordained, that the Subcollectours of every Parochine, ſhall not be obliged to carry the money received by them farther then their own Pariſh, and at fartheſt, to the head Burgh of the ſhire, and the Sub-collectour ſhall be obliged to receive the ſame, and make payment thereof to the generall collectour, as is above ſpecified.</p>
            <p>And becauſe theſe who takes pains in the ſaid collection, well the ſaid Sub-collectours, Collectors of Pariſhes, Clerks in the ſhires, Clerk of the ſaid collection, and others to be imployed in the ſaid ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, will deſerve to have certain fees and allowance granted to them.</p>
            <p>It is therefore ſtatute and ordained, that ane roll be made thereof, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the ſaids eſtates, or by ſome to be appointed from them, which rolls being ſo made and ſet down, the ſame ſhall be regiſtred in the books of convention, and extracts given forth thereof, to the effect eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man may know his own due.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152724:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>It is hereby declated, that no exemption ſhall be granted to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons whatſoever, except onely the lands, rents, annuall rents, and others dueties mortified to Colledges, Schools, Hoſpitalls, and for upholding of Kirks, and Bridges, and the Lord Chancellor, and fifteen ordiner Lords of Seſſion allannerly.</p>
            <p>It is alwayes declared, that this preſent manner of ingathering of the ſaid loane and taxation ſhall no wayes prejudge any perſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in ſucceeding taxations, but that every mans right and claim, and all the prejudice that may ariſe anent the famine or maner thereof, whereby any man may inſtruct enorm leſion, and that he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally ſtented, is hereby ſpecially reſerved <hi>hinc inde.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
